{"tossups": [{"question": "James Wilkinson conspired with this man to create a monarchy in the American west with support from Spain. This man, Thomas Jefferson\u2019s first Vice President, went to Weehauken, New Jersey to settle a personal dispute with a former Secretary of the Treasury. For ten points, name this man who killed Alexander Hamilton in an 1804 duel.", "answer": "Aaron<b> Burr</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This organization absorbed Maktab al-Khidamat after the death of Abdullah Azzam in a car bombing. A pair of attacks in Dar es Salaam and Nairobi on August 7, 1998, was orchestrated by this organization; those attacks on U.S. embassies prompted its leader to be placed on the FBI\u2019s Most Wanted list. Khalid Sheikh Mohammed and Zacarias Moussaoui were members of this group until their arrest for planning and knowledge of another of this group\u2019s attacks. For ten points, name this Islamic terrorist group that perpetrated the September 11th attacks under Osama bin Laden.", "answer": "<b> al-Qaeda</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Former President of Sears Julius Rosenwald was asked by this man to serve on the board of directors for an institute he headed. This man advised his people to \u201cCast down your bucket where you are\u201d in his\u201cAtlanta Compromise\u201d speech, which was opposed by the formulator of the \u201cTalented Tenth\u201d doctrine, W.E.B. DuBois. For ten points, name this African-American leader of the Tuskegee Institute.", "answer": "Booker T.<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man, who introduced the litmus test for differentiating acids and bases, used Robert Hooke\u2019s air pump to refute contemporary claims that vacuums don\u2019t exist. He coined the modern usage of the term\u201celement\u201d in 1661\u2019s<em> The Sceptical Chemist</em>. For ten points, name this English scientist whose namesake gas law describes how, at constant temperature, the pressure and volume of a gas are inversely related.", "answer": "Robert<b> Boyle</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "Thomas Newcomen patented the first successful one of these devices, which was used to pump water out of mines. Hero of Alexandria\u2019s aeliopile was a progenitor to this device, and John Smeaton created a competitor one of these products in England in the 1750s. Matthew Boulton worked to manufacture these devices with a man who installed a separate condenser to improve the efficiency of these devices. For ten points, name this invention, refined by James Watt, which provided power for the First Industrial Revolution in England.", "answer": "<b> steam engine</b> (prompt on partial) Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This player was selected one pick before David Greenwood after his team won a coin flip against the Chicago Bulls for the number one pick in the 1979 draft. In his final year at Michigan State, he defeated Larry Bird\u2019s Indiana State in the NCAA championship game. This co-owner of the Dodgers started a foundation in 1991 to raise awareness of AIDS after he announced that he was HIV positive. For ten points, name this Hall of Fame point guard for the Los Angeles Lakers.", "answer": "Earvin \u201cMagic\u201d<b> Johnson</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In Florence, this commodity was produced by the Arte de Lana, and the Ciompi [CHOMP-ee] was an uprising of workers with this commodity. Production of this commodity was the cornerstone of the medieval English economy, where it drove the adoption of enclosure and was exported to the Flemish cloth trade. Eventually replaced in some part by Venetian-imported silk, for ten points, name this material, which one can obtain by shearing a sheep.", "answer": "<b> wool</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The goals of this agreement had been brought up earlier by John Slidell, and this treaty put an end to the war that began with the Thornton Affair. A failed clause in this treaty that would have outlawed slavery in the territories it acquired was known as the Wilmot Proviso, and the United States paid $15 million in this agreement to gain the lands north of the Rio Grande. For ten points, name this 1848 treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Guadalupe Hidalgo</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s police operates a \u201cblack site\u201d at Homan Square, where lawyers are not allowed to speak with clients. In October 2014, Jason Van Dyke, a member of this city\u2019s police, shot Laquan McDonald 16 times; in November 2015, Van Dyke was charged with murder in Cook County. For ten points, name this Midwestern city where video of the McDonald shooting was released against the wishes of its mayor Rahm Emanuel.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b> <b>Second Quarter</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Hannibal\u2019s War, also known as the Torstensson War, was a subsidiary of this larger conflict, which saw Christian IV of Denmark sign the Treaty of L\u00a8ubeck after being defeated by Albrecht von Wallenstein. Frederick V was deposed after the Battle of White Mountain early in this war, which saw one side win the battle of L\u00a8utzen despite the death of their king, who had earlier defeated Count Tilly at the Battle of Breitenfeld. Gustavus Adolphus died in, for ten points, what war, largely between Protestant and Catholic alliances?", "answer": "<b> Thirty Years\u2019</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Key insight into the cause of this event was provided by the Strubbe Tape. Glenn Frank prevented violent retaliation against the perpetrators off this event, which was sparked by opposition to the invasion of Cambodia. Mary Ann Vecchio\u2019s screaming over Jeffrey Miller\u2019s dead body was captured in an iconic photograph after, for ten points, what massacre of four students by the Ohio National Guard in 1970?", "answer": "<b> Kent State</b> shootings (or<b> Kent State</b> massacre or equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "At this city\u2019s LEMD airport, Txeroki [\u201dCherokee\u201d] used a van bomb to kill Carlos Palate. Another event in this city targeted four cercanias at its Atocha station and was wrongly blamed on the ETA by the outgoing Prime Minister, Jose Aznar, causing his party to lose his country\u2019s general election. On March 11, 2004, Al-Qaeda bombed four trains in for ten points, what capital of Spain?", "answer": "<b> Madrid</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A king of this country formed the International African Association and sent Henry Morton Stanley to explore land for him. This country\u2019s independence movement started</b> <b>after a riot at a performance of the (+)</b> <b>opera</b><em><b> The Mute Girl of Portici</b></em><b>.</b> <b>This country</b> <b>signed the Treaty of London, which was dismissed as a \u201cscrap of paper,\u201d leading Britain to enter a war started by the (*) </b> assassination of Franz Ferdinand after this country\u2019s neutrality was violated. For ten points, name this country that split from the Netherlands with capital at Brussels.", "answer": "<b> Belgium</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A man without this school of thought is described as a \u201cdog tied to a cart\u201d by its second leader, who worked as a water carrier at night. A crippled former-slave who taught this</b> <b>school had his works published by his pupil (+)</b> <b>Arrian in the</b><em><b> Discourses</b></em><b>: that man was</b> <b>Epictetus. This movement\u2019s later authors included an advisor to Nero, (*)</b> Seneca, and it was founded by Zeno of Citium in Athens around 300 BC. For ten points, name this Hellenistic philosophy which preached self-restraint and virtue.", "answer": "<b> Stoic</b>ism", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>The Gatun Lake was formed during the building of this structure, where William C. Gorgas worked to prevent the spread of yellow fever. Omar (+) Torrijos negotiated a treaty with Jimmy Carter that transferred this structure to Torrijosâ€™ nation in 1999. This structure, built between (*) </b> 1907 and 1914, includes six locks and is crossed by the Bridge of the Americas. For ten points, name this artificial waterway in Central America that connects the Caribbean Sea to the Pacific Ocean.", "answer": "<b> Panama Canal</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>This specific concept was described as the \u201cheart of a heartless world\u201d by one thinker.\u201cThey keep you doped with\u201d this concept, \u201csex, and TV\u201d according to John Lennon\u2019s</b> <b>\u201cWorking Class Hero.\u201d In 2008, (+)</b> <b>Barack Obama explained that \u201cit\u2019s not surprising\u201d</b> <b>Barack Obama explained that \u201cit\u2019s not surprising\u201d</b> <b>that unemployed small-town people \u201cget bitter\u201d and \u201ccling to (*)</b> <b>that unemployed small-town people \u201cget bitter\u201d and \u201ccling to (*)</b> guns or\u201d this concept. For ten points, name this concept, described by Karl Marx as the \u201copium of the people,\u201d whose varieties include Christianity.", "answer": "<b> religion</b> (do not accept other terms) Page 9", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>One ruler of this empire supposedly had her husband Romanos III killed while taking a bath. That ruler was from this empire\u2019s Macedonian dynasty whose namesake renaissance</b> <b>saw the creation of the (+)</b> <b>Book of Ceremonies. That ruler, Empress Zoe, continued the</b> <b>veneration of (*)</b> icons, which reversed this empire\u2019s earlier policy of Iconoclasm. For ten points, name this empire whose capital was Constantinople, and was formerly the Eastern Roman Empire.", "answer": "<b> Byzantine Empire</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The novel</b><em><b> Ice Candy Man</b></em><b> centers around this historical event, and a novel awarded the\u201cBooker of Bookers\u201d revolves around the consequences of this event.</b><em><b> Freedom at Midnight</b></em> <b>is a non-fiction work that describes the (+)</b> <b>atrocities that occurred during this historical</b> <b>atrocities that occurred during this historical</b> <b>event, and children such as Shiva \u201cof the Knees\u201d and Parvati-the-witch have (*)</b> <b>event, and children such as Shiva \u201cof the Knees\u201d and Parvati-the-witch have (*)</b> special powers because they were born during this event. For ten points, name this August 15, 1947 event that was chronicled by Salman Rushdie in<em> Midnight\u2019s Children</em> in which two countries were created.", "answer": "<b> Partition</b> of<b> India</b> (accept<b> India-Pakistan split</b>)  (1) <b>The cathedrals of Santa Maria Novella and Santa Croce [cro-chay] in Florence</b> <b>were constructed by two rival groups of these people, and one of the most prestigious</b> <b>institution of this group was at (+) Cluny. One group of these people were founded by</b> <b>a man who received the stigmata on La Verna, which rivaled one founded by Dominic</b> <b>de Guzman. The Rule of (*)</b> St. Augustine and the Rule of St. Benedict regulate the lives of, for ten points, what people, who include Franciscans and Cistercians, are often tonsured, and live in monasteries. ANSWER:<b> Monks</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}], "bonuses": []}